<prd name="Root Discovery and Short References">

<overview>
Let users run prd commands from anywhere inside a repository and address PRD files by short references instead of full paths. The tool finds the PRD root by walking up the directory tree for a marker, the same way git locates a repository. Once a root is known, short references like `comments/likes-saves` resolve to the matching file under the discovered PRD directory.
</overview>
<implementation platform="CLI" spec="TBD" />

<requirement id="R1" name="Root discovery">
  <description>
    The tool finds the PRD root by walking upward from the current working directory and stopping at the first ancestor that carries a marker.
  </description>
  <rule id="walk_up" status="✅">Discovery starts at the current working directory and walks up through parent directories until a marker is found or the filesystem root is reached.</rule>
  <rule id="toml_marker" status="✅">A `.prd-tool.toml` file at any ancestor directory marks that directory as the PRD root.</rule>
  <rule id="convention_marker" status="✅">An ancestor directory containing `prd/index.xml` is recognized as the PRD root even without a configuration file.</rule>
  <rule id="toml_wins" status="✅">When both markers exist in the same ancestor, the `.prd-tool.toml` marker takes precedence.</rule>
</requirement>

<requirement id="R2" name="Short references">
  <description>
    Every command that takes a PRD file accepts either a path or a short reference of the form `module/feature`. Existing path-based invocations keep working.
  </description>
  <rule id="path_passthrough" status="✅">An argument that resolves to an existing file is used as-is, regardless of whether a PRD root is present.</rule>
  <rule id="module_feature_ref" status="✅">A reference of the form `module/feature` resolves to the matching PRD file under the discovered PRD directory.</rule>
  <rule id="xml_suffix_tolerated" status="✅">References ending in `.xml` resolve the same way as references without the suffix.</rule>
  <rule id="unknown_ref_error" status="✅">When a reference cannot be resolved, the tool exits with an error that names both markers it searched for and the directory where the search started.</rule>
</requirement>

<requirement id="R3" name="Discovery commands">
  <description>
    Commands that surface the discovered root and the PRDs it contains, plus a no-argument default for stats.
  </description>
  <rule id="root_command" status="✅">`prd root` prints the resolved repository root, the resolved PRD directory, and the marker source that was matched.</rule>
  <rule id="root_command_no_root_error" status="✅">When no root can be found, `prd root` exits non-zero and reports the markers it looked for and the directory where it started.</rule>
  <rule id="ls_command" status="✅">`prd ls` lists every PRD reference under the discovered PRD directory, one per line, suitable for piping; the index file itself is excluded from the listing.</rule>
  <rule id="ls_module_filter" status="✅">`prd ls module` lists only the references that live under the given module directory.</rule>
  <rule id="stats_default_index" status="✅">`prd stats` invoked with no argument operates on the index file under the discovered PRD directory.</rule>
  <rule id="ls_unfinished_filter" status="✅">`prd ls --unfinished` (also accepted as `-u`) lists only PRD references that still have unfinished work — at least one rule whose status is not ✅, or at least one bug whose status is not Fixed. References whose rules are all done and have no open or fix-pending bugs are omitted. The flag composes with the optional module argument.</rule>
  <rule id="stats_unfinished_filter" status="✅">`prd stats --unfinished` (also accepted as `-u`) restricts the report to features that still have unfinished rules or non-Fixed bugs; fully-complete features are omitted from the per-feature rows while the rollup totals continue to reflect every file scanned.</rule>
</requirement>

<requirement id="R4" name="Configuration">
  <description>
    The `.prd-tool.toml` file is optional and may override the location of the PRD directory.
  </description>
  <rule id="custom_prd_dir" status="✅">Setting `dir` under the `[prd]` section in `.prd-tool.toml` places the PRD directory at that path, resolved relative to the toml file's directory.</rule>
  <rule id="malformed_toml_tolerated" status="✅">When `.prd-tool.toml` cannot be parsed, the tool falls back to the default PRD directory rather than failing.</rule>
  <rule id="unknown_keys_ignored" status="✅">Unknown keys or sections in `.prd-tool.toml` are ignored so the schema can grow without breaking older files.</rule>
</requirement>

</prd>
